Hector Martinez

hector.mtzm6@gmail.com | (469) 343-9123 | linkedin.com/in/hectormtzm6

Back End Engineer

Motivated software engineer with experience in Java, Spring Boot, and Amazon Web Services, as well as a familiarity in front-end development and web design. Proven ability to work effectively in agile and collaborative environments, with a track record of successfully developing and maintaining complex software projects.

Experience

Back-end Developer IBM March 2021 - Current

- Involved in development, debugging, and fixing issues in various components of the AIX operating system.
- Collaborate with international team members to discuss, debug, and resolve customer-reported errors.
- Used technical skills in programming languages, including C++, C, and shell scripting to find and implement solutions.
- Developed and maintained a Spring Boot-based web application for internal use within the company, which helped speed up the configuring and redeployment of virtual machines by 50%.

Full-stack developer

Freelancer

January 2020 - March 2021

- Developed single page applications using HTML, SASS, JavaScript, and React.
- Developed static websites using HTML, CSS and JavaScript, As well as web apps using Spring Boot.

Back-End Developer Intern

Squareball Studios

June 2019 - September 2019

- Collaborated with teams located in different countries to develop and maintain projects effectively.
- Used PHP to perform CRUD operation in relational databases using SQL.
- Retrieved data from third parties APIs for display in the app.

Technical skills

Programming languages: Java 8+ | C++ | C | JavaScript | SQL | HTML | CSS Frameworks: Spring Boot | Hibernate | JUnit | React | Node.js

Databases: MySQL | PostgreSQL | MongoDB

Tools/Technologies: Amazon Web Services (AWS) | Docker | Kubernetes

Projects

University CRM June 2020

Web app developed using Java's frameworks such as Spring Boot, Hibernate and Thymeleaf. Supports CRUD operations. It counts with a REST API developed using Spring Data REST and Spring Data JPA. The CRM counts with validation and exception handling. Deployed in an Amazon Elastic Compute Cloud.

Sudoku solver February 2020

Used Java to create a Sudoku solver. The Sudoku solver uses backtracking to solve the board. The UI was made using HTML and CSS. It is validated by JavaScript functions.

Education

Bachelor of Science in Software Engineering, University of Texas at Dallas

December 2019

Languages

Written and oral fluency in Spanish (native)

Conversational and technical communication skills in English.